Doctor Who (1963) 05x03 The Ice Warriros (Episode 5)
《神秘博士》第五季第三故事 寒冰勇士 (第五小集)
【翻译】巴蛮子sz
【时间轴】巴蛮子sz
【校对】巴蛮子sz
基于 opentitles.org 英文字幕翻译
Sincro: wyxchari
Who are you?
你是谁？
I never answer questions until I'm properly introduced.
如果不先问侯我的话, 我不回答任何问题
You will answer now.
你现在就要回答
Very well. You are standing in the airlock to this spacecraft.
Unless you answer my questions within ten seconds, I will take the atmospheric pressure around you down to zero.
很好, 你正站在飞船的减压舱
如果你不回答我的问题, 在10秒钟之内我就将你那里的空气压力降到0
But... but if you do that my body will explode!
如果那样的话我的身体会爆掉的
One... two... three...
一．．．二．．．三．．．
Oh alright! Alright! But I don't think much of your hospitality!
好吧, 好吧！但我认为你实在不怎么好客
Identify yourself.
亮明你的身份
Me? I... I'm a scientist. I've come to talk with you.
我？ 我．．．我是一个科学家．我是在找你们谈话的
To help you.
来帮助你们
A scientist?
一个科学家？
Yes, yes you could call me that.
是, 是的你可以这么称呼我
You do not look like a scientist.
你看起来并不像一个科学家
Well looks aren't everything you know!
哦, 看来你并不是什么都懂
You look more like a scavenger. We killed him.
你看起来像是一个流浪汉, 我们刚杀死了一个
Well if you kill me, you'll ruin any chance you may have of escape.
如果你们杀死我, 你就毁掉了逃走的机会了
Do you think he can help us?
你觉得他可能帮助我们吗？
He cannot afford to lie. Allow him to enter.
他不敢撒谎．让他进来
Ah, thank you very much, that's very civil of you.
啊, 非常感谢, 这样就有礼貌多了
Oh, my word!
You claim to be able to help us.
你宣称说能够帮助我们
No... I am sure I can help you. On certain conditions.
不．．．我确信我能帮助你们, 在某种条件
You are our prisoner. It is we who set conditions.
你是我们的囚犯, 由我们定条件
On the contrary, it is you who are the prisoner, and I can help you!
恰恰相反, 你们才是囚犯．我能帮助你们
Not on your terms. Bring in the girl.
Now we will have two hostages.
不是按你的条件．带那个女孩儿过来．
现在我们有两个人质了
Well what good will that do? You are buried alive in the heart of this glacier.
Time is desperately short! You've got no time to bargain over hostages.
你这么做有什么好处? 你们被困在冰山的中间, 快被活埋了
已经迫在眉睫了, 你没有时间讨价还价
Inside our spaceship, we are safe.
And with you here, your base will dare not use their secret weapon against us.
在我们飞船里面, 我们是安全的
加上你也在这里, 你们的基地不敢使用他们的神秘武器来对付我们
Weapon? But, but the ioniser is not a weapon!
武器？ 但是, 那个离子器不是武器！
You know how it works?
你知道他是怎么工作的？
Yes of course! It'll melt the ice and set you free!
当然知道, 那是用来融化冰川的, 只会把你们放出去
You're hurting me!
你伤到我了
Victoria!
Oh Doctor!
喔, 博士
Victoria.
Oh dear but they've got you too.
哦, 天啊他们把你也抓住了
It's alright. We are not beaten yet.
没事的, 我们还没被打倒
Jamie...
Jamie 呢？
He's alive!
他还活着
If what you say is true, why have you not freed us before?
如果你说的是真的, 为什么之前没有给我们自由？
Well, there are difficulties.
哦, 这里有些困难
What are they?
什么困难
Well...
这个．．．
You will tell us.
你得告诉我们
...Well it's not... it's not much farther now, lad.
．．．这个, 不是．．．不太太远了, 小子
How far are we?
还有多远
Well, we're at the edge of the woods fringing the camp perimeter.
我们在林子边缘了, 前面就是基地的营地了
Can we not rest a while?
我们不能歇一下吗？
I think so - but a couple of minutes, no more.
我觉得可以 - 不过就几分钟, 不能太长
Aye, you're right. The Doctor needs help right away.
啊, 你说得对, 博士现在正需要帮助呢
I wasn't thinking only of the Doctor.
我考虑的不仅仅是博士
Wolves!
有狼！
Yes. Here we're more or less safe, but the last stretch is open country.
是的, 但我们这里还算是安全的, 但(fixme)
I don't help much, do I?
恐怕我帮不上忙了, 是吧
Well I'm not exactly a man of action myself. Storr should be here now, I miss him.
我自己也不是个擅长动手的人, Storr 在这里就好了, 我想念他
Have you no weapons?
你没有武器吗？
Arden's tranquiliser gun, that's all.
Arden 的麻醉枪, 只有这个
Aye, it's not much.
啊, 作用不大
Storr was a huntsman. An expert with a bow and arrow.
Storr 以前是个猎人, 很善于用弓箭
Uhh, it's no good wishing.
唉, 说这个也没用了 (fixme)
Well, I'd better carry on.
我们还是继续吧
Aye, lead on McDuff.
是啊, 带路吧 fixme
Keep very still.
千万别动
So, you are afraid of us?
看来, 你害怕我们？
No, but of your ship. If the ioniser sets off a nuclear holocaust, it will all have be in vain.
不, 怕的是你的船．如果离子器不小心引发了核反应, 一切都将消于无形了
That is good. In that case you dare not act.
这很好, 这种情况下你也不敢乱来
But if you thought there would be no explosion?
但如果你觉得不会发生爆炸呢？
Well?
什么？
Well in that case we'd have... we'd have no choice.
在那种情况下我们就．．．没有别的选择了
You would use the ioniser.
你将会使用你的离子器
But it wouldn't harm the ship, it would release it!
但它不会伤害到飞船的, 反而会将它释放出来
There would be floods.
这里会被水淹没
Our engines would be useless.
我们引擎就会失效
We would be at your mercy.
我们就只能求你们怜悯了
Why did you come here?
你为什么来这里？
To spy? To betray us?
做间谍？背叛我们？
But you could not hope to escape to tell the tale.
但你不可能再活着逃离这里, 去讲述你的故事了
Oh, I always live in hope.
和, 我永远都活在希望里
You have some kind of communicator.
你带着某种通讯设备
You do realise, don't you, that after a certain point, my base will...
看来你发现了, 是吧．过了一定的时间点, 我的基地就会．．．
...have to activate the ioniser regardless of the consequences?
．．．激活离子器, 不管后果是什么
And destroy you and themselves as well?
不惜杀死你, 杀死他们自己？
Is that what would happen?
这可能发生吗？
Give it to me.
把它给我
Ah, they would never know.
啊, 他们永远也不会知道
They would never know.
他们永远也不会知道
The Doctor. You heard what he said.
博士说的, 你都听到了
Regardless of the consequences. Yes. Yes, he's telling us to take the risk.
不计后果．是的．他在跟我们说要冒这个风险
But we can't give the computer the information it needs. It can't instruct us.
但我们还不能给电脑足够信息, 它没法分析出指令
Can the ioniser hold?
离子器能稳住吗？
Present power it's... steadily losing ground. But we dare not increase!
当前的能量．．．正在慢慢地流失．我们不敢加大功率
Summary of orders to all World loniser Stations: The new equation originated from Brittanicus Base
will be adopted to conditions prevailing in each sector.
All bases will prepare to use full ioniser attack on the ice in concerted action.
Zero hour in six hours exactly. Report readiness one hour.
发往全球各离子站的指令概述：要求在各区域普遍采用大不列颠基地的新方程式．
所有基地需要按预定程序对冰川施行最大功率的离子器攻击．
在六个小时内不间断执行(fixme)．请在一个小时内报告准备情况
We can't do it.
我们没法执行这个
But if we don't the whole plan must fail.
如果我们不执行, 整个计划就会失败
But if we act and there is an explosion... apart from destroying this base, the contamination could easily...
但如果我们执行, 就有可能引发爆炸．．．不仅仅是这个基地被摧毁, 整个围困计划就可能轻易地．．．
We must state our problem to World Control, now.
我们必须向世界控制中心陈述我们的情况, 现在就要
No wait! We'll give our computer all the information we have.
等一下！我们要把我们拿到的所有情况提交到电脑
It isn't enough!
那还是不够
It may be. Er, it may be.
只是可能, 哦, 只是可能
I know what the computer will say.
我知道电脑会怎么说
No no no no no. Let the computer speak for itself.
不不不, 让电脑自己说
There's only one answer it can give!
它只可能给出一种答案
Come on, quickly. Put the situation to the computer.
别说了, 快吧．把情况报给电脑
Do as you're told!
你没有听到吗！
He's sizing us up.
它在打量我们
Can you not run for it?
你就不能跑吗？
I don't intend to leave you here as...
我可没打算把你留在这里．．．
Well the gun! Use the gun!
枪！用枪！
I could hit the side of the mountain. I'm a scientist, not a gladiator.
我可能打中的是山崖, 我是一个科学家, 不是一个角斗士
Well at least you can try!
至少要得试一试！
Alright. Cross your fingers. Here goes.
好吧, 你祈祷吧．开始了
Quick get me out of here, I'll tackle him! Get a hold of yourself man! Quick, he's nearly on us!
快把我从这里弄出来, 我来对付它！控制住自己, 朋友！快啊, 它过来了
Set up all circuits to new equation. And wait. Further information essential before decision can be taken.
Prepare to notify World Control in event of emergency.
已按新方程式设定所有线路, 等待执行．在决策之前任何重要信息可继续提交．
请做好准备, 一有紧急情况就通知世界控制中心
Of course, the computer's right. We must be prepared. And we must wait.
当然．电脑是正确的．我们必须做好准备, 我也必须等待
It is the answer I expected.
这正是我期望的答案
But you don't realise why it made this choice, do you?
但你并不清楚它为什么做出这个选择, 是吧？
Because it is the most logical answer in the circumstances.
因为这是当前情况下最符合逻辑的答案
Of course. And because it's so logical, it can't gamble, it can't take risks.
当然．正因为它是最符合逻辑的, 它不可能赌博, 不可能冒风险
That is its function. To be totally impartial. To serve the community.
那正是它的功能．做到完全公正, 服务于社区
Exactly. And one more aim in its life: to survive.
正是如此．它的生命就一个目的：生存
It has given us its decision.
它已经给了我们它的决策
It is no decision. The computer is playing for time.
那不是一个决策, 电脑只是在拖延时间
Now listen! All of you! We risk destruction either by a radioactive explosion, or, by the slow grind of the glaciers.
都听着, 你们所有人！我们现在要么会被放射性的爆炸立刻毁掉,要么被冰川慢慢碾压
Now there you see that the ice has advanced 100 metres today. Now either way...
你们可以看到冰山今天已经前进了100米, 所以要么．．．
The computer is destroyed.
电脑已经坏掉了
So that, by demanding a decision, we are asking it to commit suicide.
这种情况下, 我们要求电脑给出一个决策, 就等于要求它自杀
It can't do that!
它做不到！
Then what is the answer?
那答案是什么？
We can escape. There's still time to evacuate.
我们可以逃走, 现在撤离还来得及
Perhaps you could face world opinionata. I couldn't.
也许你可以面对全世界的指责 - 我不行
You must notify World Control eventually. The other bases will be waiting.
最终你还是得通知世界控制中心, 其它的基地还在等着呢
I will decide exactly when. For now we do as the computer says.
Prepare the ioniser, and wait. Now, complete data check please, Miss Garrett.
正是那时它会做出决策的．现阶段我们按电脑说的做．
准备好离子器, 然后等着．请完成数据检查, Gattett 小姐
Miss Curtis, report to me the moment mark four reaches one-five-oh-oh. One-three-seven-nine, now.
Curtis 小姐, 第四个读数到达1500的时候请向我报告．现在是1379
Well, what do you feel about all this Walters? Bet you didn't think you'd have ice monsters
and things like that to deal with when you volunteered for the job, did you?
你对这一切怎么想, Walters？ 你没有想到要对付这些冰雪怪物吧
诸如此类东西 - 在你报名参加这项工作的时候, 是不？
Well, did you?
是吗？
I didn't volunteer.
我没有报名
Ah, yes, well... good man, anyway.
啊, 是的, 很好．．．不错, 不管怎么说
Penley! Penley, are you alright!
Penley! Penley, 你没事吧
I'll get up...
我得起来
You sure you're alright?
你确定你没事吧
Well he's clawed me, that's all.
它抓伤了我, 没别的
Now we better get away quick. He won't be any friendlier when he wakes up!
我们最好赶紧走．它要是醒过来就不可能对我们友好了
Close engine room. Well?
关闭引擎室． 怎样？
It's an ion reactor, isn't it? Hmm. It could be dangerous, but it wouldn't necessarily explode.
这是一个离子反应器, 对吧？它是有点危险, 不过不会轻易就爆炸
True. But your friends do not know that.
的确, 但你的朋友们不知道这个
Now why don't you let us help you?
那为什么不让我们来帮你们？
We can get what we want without your help.
没有你们的帮助, 我们也能得到我们需要的
But, but what else do you need, apart from escaping from the ice?
但你们还需要什么呢？不就是从冰上逃走？
We have had enough of your questions. Now you will give me answers.
我们已经受够了你这些问题．现在你得给我们些答案了
Well, I've told you all I can about the ioniser.
在离子器方面, 我能告诉你们的都已经告诉你们了
That is only a toy. The base - what is its power source?
那只是一个玩具．关于基地 - 它的能量来源是什么？
Why on earth do you want to know that?
你为什么想知道这个？
Answer.
回答
Oh, so that's what you need is it?
哦！那正是你们需要的东西, 对不？
Answer the Commander's questions.
回答指挥官的答案
Fuel! Fuel for your reactor! And suppose I don't tell you?
燃料！你们的反应器需要燃料！假设我不告诉你呢？
The girl dies, now.
这个女孩儿就得死, 现在
Doctor, don't tell them!
博士, 别告诉他们
Yes, you'll find what you need at the base.
好吧, 你可以在基地找到你们需要的东西
You shouldn't have!
你不应该的
But you, you won't find Leader Clent easy to persuade. He's a very obstinate man!
不过, 你们会发现组长 Clent 不太容易被说服．他是一个倔强的人
He will listen to our sonic cannon.
他会听命于我们的音速炮的
We must act quickly, Commander.
我们必须感觉行动, 指挥官
Isbur and Rintan, wait for me at the entrance to the cave.
Zondal, you will man the sonic gun.
Isbur 和 Rintan, 在洞窟门口等这我．
Zondal, 你带上音速枪
You won't succeed! You can't be so inhuman.
你们不会成功的, 你们不能这么没有人性
We only fight to win.
我们坚决战斗, 争取胜利
lon density reading at 1000?
离子浓度到了1000了吗
74 _.
2000?
62 _.
3000?
43.3 _.
4000?
39 _.
5000?
35 _.
Reception check-point to Leader Clent.
前台呼叫组长 Clent
Yes, what is it?
我就是, 什么事？
Two new arrivals, Sir.
来了两个人, 先生
Well I don't wish to be disturbed by trifles!
我可不希望被这些琐事打扰
These aren't scavengers Sir. It's the lad that came with the Doctor and Scientist Penley.
他们不是流浪汉, 先生．是跟着博士来的那个小伙子, 还有科学家 Penley
What?
什么
Clent, I must talk to you. I have news of the Doctor.
Clent 我必须跟你谈谈, 我有博士的消息
Walters!
你去!
Bring the arrivals to me at once.
把来的两个人立刻带过来
Sir.
好的
Density compensator setting, please.
请给出浓度补偿器设置
Density compensator setting: zero-three-nine. Seven-seven-seven. Zero-one. Sequence ends.
浓度补偿器设置：039, 777, 01, 播报完毕
Take all systems up to this level. Everything seems to be proceeding satisfactorily.
将所有系统调整到这个水平．一切好像进行得还不错
Is it?
是吗？
What's wrong?
怎么了？
Penley's come back.
Penley 回来了
Of his own choice?
他自愿回来的？
Apparently.
看来是
Why?
为什么？
We shall soon see. If he tries to start any trouble...
我们一会儿就明白了．如果他打算捣什么乱．．．
Well, he can't be allowed to interfere with the program. Not at this stage.
我们不可能让他干涉我们的程序, 都到了现在这个地步了
No. I no longer need to be tolerant with him. 'Cause he's no longer my equal - he's an outsider.
不, 我不需要再忍受他了． 因为他不再是个对手(fixme) - 他是个外人
Come on then.
过来吧
Put him over here.
把他放在这里
Take it easy.
轻一点
Rest on that Jamie.
躺在这上面 Jamie
Thank you.
谢谢你
Alright there, lad?
还好吧, 小伙子
Thank you.
谢谢你
No stay, Walters. You may be needed.
等一下, Walters, 可能还需要你
I'm not liable to be violent.
我不打算大闹一场
What do you want?
你想干什么？
Well I brought this lad. He's in desperate need of medical supervision.
我带这个小伙子过来．他迫切需要医护
We are not a first-aid center.
我们这里不是急救中心
He's paralysed.
他瘫痪了
How did it happen?
怎么造成的？
He was shot down by the warriors' guns.
他被那些寒冰勇士的枪射中了
Well thank heavens. Their weapons don't deal fatal blows.
啊谢天谢地, 他们的武器不是致命的
Well they killed Arden.
但他们杀死了 Arden
Look you've got to help.
你必须得帮忙了
Er, yes of course boy. Um, Walters will take you to the Medi-Control Centre.
呃, 当然是, 小伙子．呜, Walters 会把你带到医疗中心去
No I didn't mean me, I meant Victoria and the Doctor!
Look, they're inside the alien spaceship! You've got to help them.
不, 我不是说我, 我是说 Victoria 和博士
你看, 他们在外星飞船里, 你必须得帮助他们
That isn't possible.
那是不可能的
Well why not? You've got to do something!
为什么不？你必须得做点什么
No, we lost contact with the Doctor over an hour ago. I'm afraid there's no hope.
不, 我们在一个小时前就跟博士失去联系了, 恐怕没有希望了
You mean hope happens to be inconvenient! You've got to stick to your precious schedule, is that it?
You've got to wave your splendid ioniser about to prove that it works and never mind about human beings!
你说的没期望其实是怕麻烦！你就只考虑要紧贴你宝贵的进度计划, 是不是？
你就只想着到处挥舞你的离子器, 以证明它完全可行, 从来不考虑人的死活！
The computer has decided!
电脑已经做出决策了！
The compu... Override it! Let the ioniser wait. The computer isn't gonna fall apart because it has to mark time for an hour!
电脑．．．取消它! 离子器可以让它歇着．电脑又不会散架, 我们不是要再等一个小时吗？
We are marking time. We're not using the ioniser under instructions from the computer itself.
我们是在待命． 在电脑的指令下, 我们现在并没有开启离子器
Why?
为什么
The spaceship may contain a reactor system that could wipe us off this island if we cause it to explode.
那个飞船的反应器可能会因此而爆炸, 从而把我们从这个岛上都给抹去
So what are you gonna do?
那你们打算怎么办？
We obey the computer. We will wait.
我们听电脑的, 现在就待命
Wait? But that's suicide! The glacier's practically on top of us!
待命？这简直是自杀啊！冰山可切切实实在我们头上！
We still have time in hand.
我们手头还有时间
Yes, but if the Doctor, if he's...
是, 但是如果博士, 如果他．．．
No.
不
If the Doctor doesn't contact you, what hope is there?
如果博士不再联系你们, 还有什么希望？
There is hope.
还是有希望
Oh don't be a fool, Clent! You're not a man, you're just a machine's slave.
哦别犯傻了, Clent! 你不是一个人, 你就是一个电脑奴隶
Don't you spit your stupid liberty in my face, Penley.
We know your kind of freedom - freedom to run away - from responsibilities, from service, from moral judgement.
I may be a physical coward, Penley, you're a coward in the mind.
别我在面前喷你那些愚蠢的自由, Penley
我们知道你那种自由 - 逃走的自由, 免于责任的自由, 免于义务的自由, 免于道德判断的自由
我可能在行动上有些怯懦, Penley, 你在思想上是个懦夫
Well at least I have a mind and not a _ junction box. I would act, but you daren't.
And so you're going to be destroyed, along with your mechanical master.
至少我还有思想, 而不是个意识接线盒．我会行动, 但你不敢
所以你会被毁灭, 带着你的机器主人一起
Look, you've got to help us man.
嘿, 你必须得帮帮我们
Jamie, I don't think you're...
Jamie, 我并不认为你．．．
Jamie, take it easy.
Jamie, 冷静点
Ahh! Now, get them out of here!
啊！ 现在把他们给我赶出去！
You'd better take them to the Medi-Control Centre. Get someone to look at the boy.
Make sure there's a guard for when they come to.
你最好带他们去医护中心．找个人看一下这个孩子．
确保他们醒来的时候有一个保安在旁边．
Right. Get two guards to control.
对．叫两个保安到控制室来
Penley - he's nothing!
Penley - 他什么也不是！
Our trust is in the great computer. With its aid, we cannot fail.
我们只信任伟大的电脑．有它的帮助, 我们不可能失败
They are now outside their base.
他们现在在基地外面了
Stand by, gun control. Take target readings.
准备, 射击手．接收目标位置参数
Ready.
就绪
Vertical bearing: minus point nine.
纵轴：-0.9
Lateral bearing: three-five.
侧轴: 35
Prepare to charge to frequency three-five.
准备提升到频率35
Frequency three-five.
频率35
It's all right Victoria, don't cry.
没事的 Victoria, 不要哭
It's alright. There's nothing to be afraid of.
没事的, 没有什么可害怕的
But if Varga Rintan is triumphant, then you will have cause to cry.
不过如果 Varga 和 Rintan 得胜的话, 你们就有得哭了
Come along, Victoria, blow. Blow.
来吧, Victoria, 轰一下, 轰
That's better, that's better.
这就好多了, 好多了
We can try and escape with this.
我们得试试这个, 逃走就靠它了
What is it?
这是什么东西？
Ammonium sulphide.
硫化氨
Ammonium sulphide? It's only a stink bomb.
硫化氨? 只不过是一个臭味弹
Yes, you've had the benefits of a classical education. Yes, it is what you'd call a stink bomb.
是的, 你还是从传统教育获得了不少收益啊．是的, 这就是你说的臭味弹
What use is that?
那有什么用？
You'd be surprised. Harmless to humans, but to aliens very possibly deadly!
你会大吃一惊的．对人类是无害的, 但对于外星人来说可能就是致命的！
The gun is now ready, Commander.
枪已经准备好了, 指挥官
Good Zondal. We will now contact the scientists.
On my command you will fire once. Do you understand?
很好 Zondal, 我们这就联系这些科学家
我一声令下你们就发射, 明白了吗？
Yes, Commander.
是的, 指挥官
Good.
很好
Zondal! Zondal, look!
Zondal! Zondal, 你看！
What is it?
这是什么
Look!
看啊
Do not try any tricks.
别想耍花样
There's, there's water, seeping into the ship. Just there.
这里, 这里有一些水, 渗到飞船里面来了, 就在那儿
Er, over in the corner there.
呃, 就在那个角落
You tricked me. There is no water.
你耍我, 根本就没有水
What is that? Let me have it. Give it to me at once.
那是什么东西？ 把它给我, 马上把它给我
Zondal! Zondal fire!
Zondal! Zondal 开枪！
Fire now! Zondal fire! Zondal fire! Fire now!
马上开枪！Zondal 开枪！Zondal 开枪！马上开枪！